[{"question":"Which one of the following in India, is a hotspot of biodiversity","a":"(a) Sunderbans","b":"b) Eastern Ghats","c":"c) Western Ghats","d":"(D) Gangetic Plain","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Genetic diversity in agricultural  crops is threatened by","a":"(a) Introduction of high yielding varieties","b":"(b) Intensive use of fertilisers","c":"(C) Intensive intercropping","d":"d) Intensive use of biopesticides","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":". Antilopa cervicapra or Black Buck is","a":"(a) Vulnerable","b":"b) Endangered","c":"(c) Critically endangered","d":"(d) Extinct in the wild","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following species is endangered?","a":"(a) Panthera leo persica","b":"(b) Python molurus","c":"(c) Chelonia mydas","d":"(d) Siberian crane","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Exotic species","a":"(a) are often endangered.","b":"(b) usually increase biodiversity","c":"(C) often enhance the habitat for native species","d":"(d) usually reduce biodiversity","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"What is genetic diversity?","a":"(a) The total genetic information contained within all individuals of species ","b":"(b) The total phenotypic information contained within all individuals of a species","c":"(C) The variety of life-forms on Earth","d":"d) The variety of biotic communities in a region along with abiotic components","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following is the most serious threat to biodiversity ","a":"(a) Competition from exotic species","b":"(b) Commercial harvesting","c":"(c) Habitat destruction","d":"(d) Overexploitation","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"National Park associated with Rhinoceros is:","a":"(a) Kaziranga","b":"(b) Ranthambore","c":"(c) Corbett","d":"(d)  Valley of Flowers","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"In which state \"Periyar National park\" is present?","a":"(a) Karnataka","b":"(b) Maharashtra","c":"(C) Madhya Pradesh","d":"(d) Kerala","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"In India, we find mangoes with different  flavours, colours, fibre content, sugar content and even shelf-life. The large variation is on account of","a":"(a) Species diversity","b":"(b) Induced mutations","c":"c) Genetic diversity","d":"(d) Hybridisation","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"For conservation of tiger \"a tiger project' is being run in the country. How many tiger reserves are there under this project","a":"(a) 10","b":"(b) 14","c":"(c) 12","d":"(d) More than 16","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The proportionate number of individuals of The proportionate number of individuals Of an area is called","a":"(a) Species diversity","b":"(b) Species richness","c":"c) Diversity index","d":"(d) Species evenness","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Biosphere reserve project was started in India during","a":"(a) 1984","b":"(b) 1985","c":"(C) 1986","d":"(d) 1989","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"In a biosphere reserve, the area surrounding the core zone is called: ","a":"(a) Buffer zone","b":"(b) Transition zone","c":"(C) Peripheral zone","d":"(d) Development zone","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which one of the following shows concept of species-area relationship","a":"(a) The number of species in an area increases with the size of the area","b":"b) Larger species require larger habitat areas than do smaller species","c":"(c) Most species within any given area are endemic.","d":"d) The larger the area, the greater the extinction rate","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The percentage of forest cover recommended  by National Forest Policy (1988) is:","a":"(a) 33% for plains and 67% for hills","b":"(b) 37% for plains and 63% for hills","c":"(c) 20% for plains and 70% for hills","d":"(d) 23% for plains and 77% for hills","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following does not Constitute Habitat destruction ","a":"(a) Fishing","b":"(b)  Logging","c":"c) Burning forests","d":"(d) Filling in wetlands","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Why do migratory  species present special Critical  preservation challenges? ","a":"a) Because they are endemic, they are especially susceptible to habitat destruction.","b":"b) Their conservation may require international  cooperation when they require habitats in different Countries","c":"(c) They are often prone to population number  decline during their long migratory journeys. ","d":"(d) They reside in biodiversity hot spots that  are most susceptible to habitat degradation.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Biosphere Reserves differ from National Parks  and Wildlife Sanctuaries because in the former:","a":"(a) human beings are not allowed to enter.","b":"(b) people are an integral part of the system.","c":"(c) plants are paid greater attention than the animal","d":"d) living organisms are brought from all over the world and preserved","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Earth Summit at Rio-de-Janeiro was related to:","a":"(a) Soil fertility","b":"b) Survey of natural resources","c":"(c) Conservation of environment","d":"(d) Prevention of afforestation","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a concern regarding habitat fragmentation ","a":"(a) Habitats can change type","b":"b) Habitats can be too small to support some Species","c":"c) It reduces dispersal ability of some animals.","d":"(d) It creates a large amount of vulnerable edge habitat","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Degree of biodiversity increases from:","a":"(a) Equator to poles","b":"(b) Polar to equator","c":"c) Low latitude to high latitude","d":"(d) Low altitude to high altitude","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The Red data Book, which lists endangered species of animals, is maintained by:","a":"(a) WWF","b":"(b) UNO","c":"(c) WHO","d":"(d) IUCN","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which animal is the symbol of WWF (World  Wildlife Fund):","a":"(a) Dolphin","b":"(b) Tiger","c":"(c) Giant Panda","d":"d) Great Indian Bustard","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which is preserved in National Park?","a":"a) Flora","b":"(b) Fauna","c":"C) Both (a) and (b)","d":"d) None of these","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"New approach of conservation is the establishment of","a":"(a) Sancturies","b":"(B) Reserve forests","c":"c) National parks","d":"d) Biosphere reserves","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Approximately 50% of total world species are  present on:","a":"a) tropical rain forest","b":"(b) temperate rain forest","c":"c) temperate deciduous forest","d":"(d) coral reefs","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The country which hosted the First World Earth Summit on conservation of environment is?","a":"(a) Spain","b":"(b) Peru","c":"(c) India","d":"(d) Brazil","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Blue whale is placed under","a":"(a) Endangered","b":"(b) Critically endangered","c":"(c) Rare","d":"d) Extinct","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which one of the following in India, is a hotspot of Bideversity","a":"(a) Sunderbans","b":"(b) Eastern Ghats","c":"(c) Western Ghats","d":"(D) Gangetic Plain","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Diversity of habitat over the total landscape is called","a":"(a) áºž diversity","b":"(b) y diversity (gamma)","c":"c) Landscape diversity","d":"d) Ecosystem diversity","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Those species whose populations have been seriously depleted and whose ultimate security  is not assured are known as: ","a":"(a) Threatened species","b":"(b) Endangered species","c":"c) Vulnerable species","d":"d) Rare species","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The greatest threat to global biodiversity is:","a":"a) natural disasters such as storms","b":"(b) pollution","c":"(C) overexploitation of natural resources.","d":"(d) human alteration of habitats","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following is Threatened by illegal trade in wildlife products ","a":"(a) Nile perch","b":"(B) Elephants","c":"c) Key deer","d":"d) Galapagos tortoises","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The taxa believed likely to join the Endangered Category in near future is called: ","a":"(a) Extinct","b":"(b) Rare","c":"(c) Vulnerable","d":"(d) Out of danger","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Red data book provides data on","a":"(a) Red flowered plants","b":"(b) Red coloured fishes","c":"(c) Endangered plants and animals","d":"d) Red eyed birds","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The most biodiversity rich zone in India","a":"(a) Gangetic planes","b":"b) Trans himalayas","c":"c) Western Ghats","d":"d)  Central India","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"In a biosphere reserve  limited human activity  is permitted in: ","a":"(a) Core zone","b":"(b) Buffer zone","c":"c) Manipulation zone","d":"D) None of these","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following represents the biodiversity of an area","a":"a) Gene","b":"b) Species","c":"(c) Ecosystem","d":"d) All of these","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The Wildlife (Protection) Act 1972 was First amended in","a":"(a) 1991","b":"(b) 1995","c":"(c) 2001","d":"d) 2007","hint":"","correct":"a"}]